Get out!
出去！
Get out! Hurry!
出去…快出去！
Inside the hut! Come on!
躲進去…快點…
Get in! Come on!
進去…快一點…
Out of here!
出去！
Don't come in! Get out!
不要再進來了…出去…
Come on! Run!
快點！快跑…
Yes, sir
是…
Is it Mehebu Clan?
馬赫坡社嗎？
Yes, sir
是…
Aim all cannons at the Mehebu Forest
砲口全部對準馬赫坡森林…
End this battle before the sun's out
太陽出來之前結束這場戰爭吧！
Tado! Kill me!
達多…
快把我殺了！
Come on!
快！
It hurts so badly!
我好痛…
Out of the way!
讓開！讓開…
Cut my head off! You hear me?
把我的頭砍下來聽不懂啊…
Get off him!
手拿開…
It's beautiful
好漂亮…
So beautiful
好漂亮啊…
Stop firing please
請停止射擊…
They ran away
他們逃掉了…
Fight till you drop! Seediq Bale!
戰死吧！賽德克巴萊…
Fire the cannons! Fire!
開砲！開砲！
We're under attack!
敵人打來了…
You damned Japanese! Get out of our territory!
可惡的日本人…滾開我們的部落…
You bastards! Get out!
混蛋…還不快滾…
That's one favor I did you Mehebus today
helping you drive our the intruders
今天幫你把異族人趕出馬赫坡一次…
Out of my way! Let me kill them!
前面讓開…我來打！
Temu, give me the bullets!
泰牧…把子彈給我！
Come on! Look out!
快點…小心前面！
Climb up there!
爬上去！
Sine! Sine!
西奈…西奈…
Sine!
西奈…
Sine! Sine!
西奈…西奈…
Stop!
站住！
Come back here!
給我站住！
You take care of him!
去照顧他…
Load the guns! Come on!
裝子彈！快！
Pawan?
巴萬…
You Japanese are finished!
日本人你們完蛋了…
Quick! - Catch him!
-快點…
-追過去！
Off with his head!
獵下他的頭！
Stop!
不要跑…
Don't let him slip away!
不要放過他…
Mouna Rudo!
莫那魯道…
Stop running!
大家不要逃了！
Kill until our blood runs out!
殺到血乾吧…
Cut off their heads like true warriors!
像戰士一樣拿下人頭…
The heavenly home of our ancestors,
here we come!
回祖靈之家唷…
I'm a chief, not your little brother
我是頭目…不是你弟弟…
Iyung! Iyung!
伊勇…伊勇…
Don't touch it, lyung
手不要碰…伊勇…
Iyung!
伊勇…
What are you doing? Move!
幹什麼…走開！
Look out! It's falling down!
倒下去了…倒下去了…
Pawan! Get out of there!
巴萬！快出來！
Pawan, get out now!
巴萬…快點出來！
Pawan!
巴萬…
Iyung! Iyung!
伊勇…伊勇…
Are you alright?
你怎麼了？
Pawan, I've got a good gun
巴萬！拿到好槍了…
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Batu! -Dakis!
-巴杜…
-達基司
Move!
走開！
Ubus!
烏布斯…
Come on! The Japanese are out!
快…日本人跑出來了…
Watch out over there!
小心那邊！
There's one behind him!
後面還有一個…
Don't go there!
不要過去！
Stop!
不要跑！
Bomb!
砲彈！
So you're Mouna Rudo
原來你就是莫那魯道…
Now I see you clearly
我看清楚你了…
Tado, how do we dodge those cannons?
達多…
怎樣才能躲過那些大砲？
Chief, let this ghost lead the way
頭目…
讓我這個鬼魂來帶路吧！
Fire!
開砲！
Look!
看！
Cherry blossoms everywhere!
櫻花開滿天了…
(Those who come forward voluntarily
will be spared)
(Come to the shelters to surrender)
l'm crossing the rainbow bridge
我要走去彼岸的那邊了…
l am Mouna Rudo
我是莫那魯道唷！
Look at the road l've trodden
看我腳步所邁開的道路！
No one's ever gonna stop us
誰也無法抵擋我們…
The determined warriors
決死的勇士啊！
We're home with our enemy's heads
看我們今天帶著首級歸來了…
We're true warriors, like budding pine leaves
像松樹嫩芽般真正的勇士啊！
You must be starved
大家都餓了吧…
and you must be exhausted
也都累了吧！
It's time to decide your future
是該決定自己未來的時侯了…
If you want to take your own life, do it
想自盡的就自盡
If you want to turn yourself in, go ahead
想投降的就投降
If you want to keep fighting..
想繼續戰鬥的…
Tado..
達多…
My dear son..
我的兒子啊…
The hero of Mehebu Clan
馬赫坡的勇者！
Lead them to fight
until you use up all your bullets
你帶他們打完最後一顆子彈吧！
Father! -Chief..
父親！
頭目…
Warriors, forgive me
戰士們！
原諒我…
Forgive me
I don't want the Japanese to insult me
in front of my people
我不願讓日本人在族人面前玩弄我
Forgive me
原諒我…
I'll be waiting for you on the mountain peak
我到山的極巔等你們…
Let's cross the rainbow bridge together
to the eternal hunting ground
一起回到彩虹彼端的美麗獵場…
Father?
父親…
Go..Seediq Bale!
去吧！
賽德克巴萊！
Chief Mouna?
莫那頭目…
Bakan,
巴岡…
bring over everyone from the chief's family
把我們家族的人都帶過來…
Iwan, go back and tell our people in the cavern
依婉…
回去告訴岩窟的族人
that those who don't want to surrender
may as well kill themselves
不想投降的就自盡吧！
I want to fight!
我要去戰鬥…
Me too! -It's over!
我也要去…
結束了…
Mouna!
莫那！
Mouna, where's your ancestral spirit?
莫那…你的祖靈在哪裡？
Where is it?
你的祖靈在哪裡…
There could be greater suffering if you survived
我怕你們承擔不住活下來…
Wipe your face clean
…把臉擦乾淨
Thank you, women and children
謝謝你們女人孩子…
for sacrificing yourselves
to complete the men's souls
成就了部落男人的靈魂…
She's awake!
醒來了…
That savage woman is awake!
那個蕃女醒來了…
Officer Kabasoa!
樺澤警部…樺澤警部…
What's going on?
-That savage woman is awake
-怎麼了？
-那個蕃女醒來了…
Is it Mahung? -Yes, sir
-是馬紅嗎？
-是…
Excuse me!
不好意思…
Let me through!
…借過
Mahung! Mahung!
馬紅…馬紅…
Mahung..
馬紅…
I'm Kabasawa. I've been to your house
我是樺澤…
我去過你們家的…
Do you remember me, Mahung?
記得嗎？馬紅…
Why did you save me?
…為什麼要救我？
My husband and children are waiting for me
我的丈夫孩子都在等我啊…
Mahong..
馬紅…
100 dollars
一百塊錢！
Son of a bitch! What are you doing?
混蛋！你們幹什麼？
Don't put it on the desk!
不要放在桌子上！
What are you looking at? Next!
看什麼？下一個…
It's only a child. You can't get 100 for it
這只是孩子，哪值一百塊？
Get it off!
拿走開！
It's Temu Mouna from Truwan Clan
這是塔羅灣的…泰牧摩那…
What child?
Don't you see the tattoos on his face?
什麼孩子，他臉上有圖騰哪！
Put it over there! What a nuisance!
拿到那邊去啦，囉嗦…
It's Tanah Robe, the Boarung chief
這是…波阿崙頭目達那哈羅拜…
One of you from Gungu Clan killed our chief
你們荷戈社殺了我們頭目…
This one is Pawan Nawi from Mehebu Clan
這是馬赫坡的巴萬那威…
Ukan! Tado!
烏干…達多…
Where are you?
你們在哪裡？
Where is that father going?
那個父親要去哪裡哪？
The father carrying a child on his back
那個父親揹著幼小的嬰孩…
is setting out to shoot the two suns in the sky
要去征伐天上的兩顆太陽了！
They go on and on for a long way
他們走了很遠很遠的路
The child grows up
那個嬰孩長大成人了…
The father dies at an old age
那個父親老死了…
The child takes his father's bow and arrows
孩子揹起了父親的弓箭
The child follows his father's footsteps
孩子繼續父親的路…
toward the rising suns
向著日出之處前進
He gets there at last
…終於到達了呀！
The child gets there at last
孩子終於到達了！
The child shoots a sun down with an arrow
孩子張弓射下了一個太陽
The sun loses its rays
太陽的光芒消失了
The dead sun becomes the moon
死去的太陽變成了月亮
He's a sun-shooting hero
他是射日的英雄！
The sun-shooting hero is returning home
射日勇士又啟程歸鄉了！
The sun-shooting hero has come a long,
long way
射日勇士走了很遠很遠的路…
The sun-shooting hero is home at last
射日勇士終於回家了！
But the hero is already gray-headed
勇士回家已經白髮蒼蒼…
l am drunk today
今天的日子我醉了
l saw him on the way
在路上我看到他了…
The boy from the freezing winter
那個來自酷寒嚴冬下的男孩
A fair-skinned boy like a budding pine leaf
如松枝嫩芽般白白的男孩
Let's dance together
一起來跳舞吧…
Let's enjoy ourselves
讓我們盡興歡聚吧！
l'm drunk today
今天的日子我醉了
Young girls, let's dance together
年輕的女孩我們一起跳舞吧…
Surrender? Why should we surrender?
投降？
為什麼要投降呢？
We've had our enemy's sake wine
我們幾個既然喝了敵人的酒
Doesn't that mean conciliation?
不就算和解了嗎？
Why do we have to surrender?
為什麼還需要投降呢？…
Tado... -Say no more!
-達多…
-不要再講了！
Come on, drink with me
來！你也喝…
Mahung, my little sister...
馬紅…
it's much easier for me to die
哥哥要求死很容易
than for you to go on living
你們要活下去卻很難…
But you must endure
你要多忍耐…
and have lots of children
要多生孩子…
Teach them everything
about the pride of our father
要教他們認識我們父親的驕傲…
Let your children have even more children
讓你的孩子們再生孩子…
and more and more..
再生孩子…
Mahung, have lots of children
馬紅…
再生孩子…
Raise them up to be proud Seediqs
and to live on with pride
要每個孩子都成為驕傲的賽德克
挺起胸膛的活著…
Do you understand?
懂嗎？
Father, Baso and I..
…我、巴索、父親
along with all our fallen people
和死去的族人們…
will be watching over you
from the rainbow bridge
都會在彩虹上看著你們…
Look! The sun is so beautiful
…你看
陽光好美啊！
Oh, my wife!
妻子呀！
ls the wine ready now?
你把酒釀好了嗎？…
Here l come, my wife and children
妻兒呀！我來了唷！
On my way to the heavenly home
of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的這路上
Wait a little longer for me please
請你們稍等一會兒
l'll be seeing you soon
我很快就趕來和你們會面了！
We're already on our way
我們已經上路了呀…
Oh my wife and children, wait a little longer
妻兒呀！再等一會兒吧…
Wait for us on the way
to the heavenly home of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的這路上等我們
Oh my wife and children, wait a little longer
妻兒呀！稍等一會兒…
We're almost there
我們已經來了…我們已經來了…
We're about to cross the road
就快要越過道路…
We'll be seeing you in no time
我們很快就要相會了！
Wait for us on the way
to the heavenly home of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的這路上等我們
Oh my wife and children, wait a little longer
妻兒呀！稍等一會兒…
We're almost there
我們已經來了…我們已經來了…
We're about to cross the road
就快要越過道路…
We'll be seeing you in no time
我們很快就要相會了！
(Pihu Sapu was beaten up to death)
(in the detention house after he got caught)
(Tado Mouna and the last surviving warriors
all committed suicide )
(Mouna Rudo disappeared without a trace )
300 warriors against thousands of soldiers
三百名戰士抵抗數千名大軍
Those survived the battle
killed themselves eventually
不戰死便自盡…
Why did I see
in such a remote mountain area in Taiwan
為何我會在這遙遠的台灣山地
the bushido of samurais
that died over a century ago in Japan?
見到我們已經消失百年的武士精神？
Is it because the cherry blossoms here
are far too red?
是這裡的櫻花開得太艷紅了嗎？
No, these flowers have bloomed early this year
不！
今年的花開早了…
It isn't the season of cherry blossoms yet
現在不應該是櫻花的季節…
(After the incident...)
(Kojima Genji instigated the Seediqs
from Toda)
(to revenge the death of their chief
Temu Walis )
(by killing all the remaining
defenseless tribesmen)
(staying in the shelter during the night)
Out of the way!
前面讓開！
(The few surviving tribesmen were forced)
Hurry up!
快一點！
(to relocate to a compound along
Peikang River)
Out of the way!
前面讓開！
(where the Japanese
could monitor them easily )
Out of the way!
(where the Japanese
could monitor them easily )
(They burned down all their remaining houses )
(before they left)
(Four years later...)
(Mouna Rudo's remains were found)
(inside a cavern,
somewhere deep in the mountains )
(Half of his body rotted to skeleton)
(while the other half
was weathered to a mummy )
(In the following year...)
(the Japanese publicly displayed
his remains and weapons )
(in a wooden crate at the exhibition
celebrating the completion)
(of Nenggao City Hall construction project)
Ah, it's for real
啊~真的啊！
(After that,
his remains disappeared once again)
l'll be arriving soon
(After that,
his remains disappeared once again)
我即將要到達…
l'll be arriving soon
到達祖靈之家！
at the heavenly home of our ancestors
Yes, it's for real
真的…是真的！
Reminisce the people from the past
懷念過去的人們啊
Here l am
我來到這裡
(After the second disappearance )
Here l am
(Mouna Rudo's remains
were recovered 39 years later)
l used to guard
these mountains and forests bravely
(Mouna Rudo's remains
were recovered 39 years later)
我曾英勇守護的山林…
l used to guard
these mountains and forests bravely
(in the specimen room
of the College of Medicine )
l used to guard
these mountains and forests bravely
(in National Taiwan University )
These are our mountains
這是我們的山唷…
Escorted by his offspring)
These are our mountains
These are our creeks
(Escorted by his offspring)
這是我們的溪唷…
These are our creeks
(after 43 years, he finally returned
to his hometown Wushe )
We're the true Seediq Bale
(after 43 years, he finally returned
to his hometown Wushe )
我們是真正的賽德克巴萊唷…
We're the true Seediq Bale
(to be buried properly )
We go hunting in the mountains
我們在山裡追獵…
We share food in our clan
我們在部落裡分享
We fetch water from the creeks
我們在溪流裡取水…
l'm willing to give my life for these
願我為此獻出我的生命…
Oh, creek! Be quiet!
溪流啊！不要再吵了…
Sisin babblers are singing
祖靈鳥在唱歌了…
Sing us a beautiful song please
請唱首好聽的歌吧！
Sing for our people
為我們的族人唱…
a song of our ancestral spirit
來自祖靈的歌…
(List of Angel Fund contributors)
l'm willing to give my life too
願我也獻出我的生命…
(List of Angel Fund contributors)
When the lightening rifts the rock
巨石雷光下
a rainbow appears
彩虹出現了…
and a proud man emerges
有一個人走來了…
A proud man emerges
一個驕傲的人走來了…
Who is this man so proud?
是誰如此驕傲啊？
lt's your offspring
是你的子孫啊…
A Seediq Bale
賽德克巴萊！
Once upon a time on Mt. White Stone
there was a big tree called Pusu Qhuni
從前從前在白石山上…
有一棵大樹，名叫波索康夫尼…
The tree trunk was half wood, half stone
他的樹身…
一半是木頭，另一半是岩石…
One day, a boy and a girl were born
from the tree trunk
有一天，他的樹身生下了一男一女
Then the couple gave birth to lots of children
後來這男女又生下了許多的孩子…
and here we are, the Seediq Bale
就是我們…真正的賽德克人…
Behold! The beautiful rainbow over the hilltop
你們看！美麗的彩虹，在山的那一頭！
My wife and children,
have you brewed the wine?
妻兒呀！你們把酒釀好了嗎？
Drink it!
The wine we offer to our ancestors' spirits
喝吧！獻給祖靈的酒！
Behold! What beautiful rainbow!
My ancestors are calling me
你們看！美麗的彩虹
是祖先在召喚我了！
My wife and children! Are you on your way
to meet our ancestors spirits?
妻兒呀！你們在通往祖靈的路上了嗎？
We should get going too
我們也該上路了
Stand still,
our people who keep the bloodline going
必須延續生命的族人呀！挺起胸膛！
We will be proud like a true Seediq
要驕傲得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits will be watching over you
from the rainbow bridge
我們死去的靈魂會在彩虹橋上看著你們
Tell every child to live on forever
告訴每個孩子，生生不息！
To live on like a true Seediq
要活得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits
will keep you company in the woods
我們死去的靈魂會在山林媕Y陪著你們
Behold! What beautiful rainbow!
My ancestors are calling me
你們看！美麗的彩虹
是祖先在召喚我了！
My wife and children! Are you on your way
to meet our ancestors spirits?
妻兒呀！你們在通往祖靈的路上了嗎？
We should be on our way too
我們也該上路了
Stand still,
our people who keep the bloodline going
必須延續生命的族人呀！挺起胸膛！
We will be proud like a true Seediq
要驕傲得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits will be watching over you
from the rainbow bridge
我們死去的靈魂會在彩虹橋上看著你們
Tell every child to live on forever
告訴每個孩子，生生不息！
To live on like a true Seediq
活得像個真正的賽德克
Our bodiless spirits
will keep you company in the woods
我們死去的靈魂會在山林媕Y陪著你們
Look! -Drink! Drink!
-你們看∼
-喝吧！喝吧！
What a beautiful sky!
-We should be on our way
-多美麗的天空呀∼
-我們該上路了！
Look! -Drink! Drink!
-你們看∼
-喝吧！喝吧！
What a beautiful sky!
-We should be on our way
-多美麗的天空呀∼
-我們該上路了！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
Children!
孩子們！
Did you see that? We see the rainbow
看見了吧！看見彩虹了唷！
We see the rainbow
看見彩虹了唷！